thank you
foreign
[Music]
episode 148 I think the new the 150th
episode will be in the new year
so today we are on number 148 so uh
before we begin let's see who all is
there on the live chat I can see they
just
XOXOXO Daniel Nicholson
Vikram Dan Charan
Albert XP Melvin Typical Gamer manohar
Saiyan Shivam Vladimir Biden technician
Rahul Tejas
done my sky yashas dilip G Herbie on
wheels
feminist Slayer mother chacher a
Rahul Zach tell everyday things
man
Stone 420 prabhakar Aditya Mr Giga child
of India Vikram Dan Charan dhiraj Tamil
Jeong Gina dilip gaurav
crazy brains me here
part
and lots and lots and lots of other
people Priyanka
um
lokesh as Menor sushant Ashima Arun and
lots of other people good evening good
day thank you so much for being on the
show on this live telecast
so let us begin with the questions as
always I've taken a whole lot of
questions let's see how many of them I
can answer I'm able to answer today so
let's go for question number one
question number one is about the G20
presidency
Aditya says please explain the
importance of the G20 presidency for
India
India is the president for 4G 20 for
2023 what opportunities does it bring to
India in terms of geopolitics and the
Voldemort says what's your take on
India's presidency in G20 how can India
use this power other than inviting
countries like Singapore or whatever
else yes
so yes India is now has now assumed the
G20 presidency India is the president of
the G20 group of Nations for one year so
first of all let's understand that this
is a rotating presidency
uh whichever nation is due to host uh
the next G20 Summit becomes the
president for one year and the G20
Summit is also allocated on a rotating
basis so the previous G20 Summit which
happened just a few a couple of months
ago was uh hosted by Indonesia in Bali
so Indonesia was the G20 president now
the next Summit is going to be in India
so India is the G20 has assumed the G20
presidency so it's a rotating presidency
it's not something that that India has
won by defeating everybody else it's not
like that it's something that every
nation in the G20 group uh gets once in
roughly 20 years or so so that's what
first of all it is now what does this
G20 presidency mean so first of all it
has no real geopolitical benefits yeah
this is more like a Prestige thing or a
status thing that yeah we are the we are
the G20 president but of course it it
brings in some tangible benefits for for
that Nation
so the nation gets to host the G20
Summit and not just one Summit but a
whole lot of events that take place
throughout the year so you get to
Showcase uh your people your
capabilities the talent that you have in
the nation
um the various institutions and
organizations that you have you get to
bring various people together from
various Nations and have them interact
with your people so uh that helps your
nation in a variety of ways you get to
show of how how whatever you have
achieved so that uh kind of enhances
your soft Power Nations like China are
really good at this you know showing off
how great they are apparently how great
they are right and so on so it is an
opportunity for each Nation to showcase
whatever is great about it whatever is
good about it you know whatever Terrence
it has and all all that
so there are events that are going to be
held in various parts of the nation in
India throughout the next year
throughout this this uh coming year and
it's gonna be a great opportunity for
lots of people in various parts of India
to interact with uh
G20 delegates from across the world in
in their particular field of expertise
and in it it helps India showcase uh the
achievements that India has done so
let's take a look at the press release
and all that uh to see what what exactly
uh this means for India where are we
one second
so let's go and take a look at this
India assumes a G20 presidency uh what
does this mean
so India has assumed the G20 presidency
from Indonesia today this is on December
1 2022 right uh this is uh less than a
month ago the group of 20 we know what
it is so that's the press release now
what else do we have
um
so India gets to set the theme of this
this presidency so the theme of India's
G20 presidency is
delegates and guests will get a great
glimpse of India's Rich cultural
heritage and the year-long India
experience so you get to Showcase your
soft power your culture India will host
over 200 meetings in over 50 cities
across 32 different work streams so a
lot of exposure to to
the rest of the world will get a lot of
exposure to what India is doing and it
will give a great opportunity for
Indians in these 32 different work
streams in 50 cities to get an exposure
to the in to the you know to
International delegates and all that so
it's great about it's great in that
perspective
um so that's what it is a theme is one
Earth one family one future all that
um what are the India's G20 priorities
this is interesting green development
climate finance and life accelerated
inclusive and resilient growth
accelerating progress on S DG's or
sustainable development goals that I
believe that's what it is
[Music]
technological transformation and digital
public infrastructure multilateral
institutions for the 21st century and
women-led development so these are the
the uh priorities that India has has set
forth for the next year and this is
going to be about 200 meetings in over
50 cities across 32 different work
streams and these are the priorities
that India is going to focus on and
India essentially is going to lead the
G20 uh grouping in in all of these
things so the first Sherpa meeting
whatever that is of the presidency has
begun is begin it's already done in the
historic city of
udaipur Rajasthan so as you can see you
have delegates from the various G20
Nations and all that yeah
and they get to see uh you know India's
culture and what India has to offer and
there are discussions and interactions
you know exchange of thoughts and ideas
and perspectives that is always great
when you're working in various fields
and all that and also there is this
science Summit so the G20 has a s20
component which is the science 20 Summit
which is also going to be held in India
so uh the last science 20 thing was the
summit was held in in Indonesia in
Jakarta September 20 and 21 yeah
um so you had something in Rome you had
something in Saudi Arabia this was it
the Rome was in 2020 21 Saudi Arabia was
2020 and so on uh so that is what
happened there and you can see the
various uh details there is a website if
it uh opens it will open eventually so
the the theme for the science 20 Summit
was recovered together recovered
together recover stronger so obviously
the theme is the pandemic and recovering
from the pandemic and that was the theme
of the uh s20 Summit hosted by Indonesia
now what about the Indian s20 Summit
it's going to be in 2023
so the the theme is disruptive science
for Innovative and sustainable
development right let's find out the
focus areas there's an Inception meeting
which is setting the stage then clean
energy for a Greener future Universal
holistic health
connecting science to society and
culture and synthesis and policy
recommendations right so I personally am
going to be involved in this process I
am going to be one of the Indian
delegates for the for so the first
meeting is going to be uh the end of
January I believe in pondicherry so I
will be participating in that and I will
I'm going to make sure that I put forth
uh proposals and uh you know ideas that
I would like to share in the
about all of these various Focus areas
so I am going to be participating in in
the science uh component of the G20 uh
uh proceedings in India so this is what
G20 the G20 presidency is about it's
about every nation whenever it gets the
opportunity to folk to Showcase first of
all to take the lead the initiative
in in deciding the focus areas in the
priorities for this year and then you
showcase uh whatever development you've
done whatever your strengths are
whatever your culture is all of that and
you hold like 200 meetings over 50
different cities you bring people
together and at the end of the year
there's the big Summit and that's what
it is like right and there could be
significant uh tangible outcomes of all
of these meetings when you have so many
meetings so many people meeting together
ideas being being exchanged
cross-pollination of ideas and good
things come out of that quite often so
that's what it's all about it's nothing
to do with geopolitics India is not
going to get any geopolitical benefits
from this it's more about showcasing
your progress your development as a
nation that you that India is now a
major power in the world India is a
strong confident vibrant Nation with
with pride in its culture and a
significant track record of scientific
progress in development and
technological development and we can
showcase all of this to the rest of the
world we would like the world to
understand and realize that we are no
longer the India of the 20th century we
are a very different Nation today so
this is the opportunity for India to do
that uh in a variety of fields and I am
going to be involved in the in the
science uh sector of that so that's what
it is about it's not going to make India
a stronger nation geopolitically and all
that but this is
in in a nutshell what the G20 presidency
is going to be about
so yeah that's what it is
question two by Tejas why has Russia
never had any colonies question credit
goes to Twitter yeah so just a couple of
hours ago somebody asked me about this
on Twitter that why has Russia never had
any colonies are you sure that Russia
has never had any economies
yes so to understand this you have to
study history and you have to look at
the map
and as we know the map is the most
is one of the highlights of the Oscar
budget show so let's go to the map
where's the map here's the map take a
look at Russia
so Russia is this nation this nation
state that straddles the northern part
of Eurasia yes
from Eastern Europe onwards
Moscow is in the eastern part of Europe
uh east of Belarus and the Baltic states
Lithuania Latvia Estonia uh Ukraine is a
well we will not touch upon Ukraine
right now it was part of the USSR
obviously and then this entire enormous
vast expanse of territory this is all
Russia all the way to the Far East of
Asia
it also includes this sakhalin island
yes the though it was once believed to
be a peninsula but now we know it's an
island
and it also includes uh the Kamchatka
Peninsula which is here yes
and the various kuril islands where
Russia has a territorial dispute with
Japan a simmering territorial dispute
that goes back more than a century
so it's an enormous expanse of territory
do you think this is all the terror this
entire territory is inhabited by
russian-speaking people is that what you
think
take a look at the map does it make any
sense that this whole entire enormous
vast expanse of territory is inhabited
by only Russians speaking people it's
not the case firstly understand the
history of Russia who are the Russian
people the Russian people are Are Slavic
people they're the largest uh uh
linguistic ethno-linguistic group within
the Slavic peoples yes there are other
Slavic peoples also for instance in
Serbia and so on the ukrainians are also
Slavic people whether they like it or
not it's the that is the case right and
the largest Slavic group is the
reference the Russians are their origin
lies in the kievan ruse about a thousand
years ago right uh so I'll not go deep
into history but the Slavs are in Roman
records nearly 2 000 years back uh
Islamic ethnic group is is tested in
Roman records nearly two thousand years
back if I if my memory serves me right
and the history of the kievan ruse
people goes back about a thousand years
their leaders were actually Vikings yeah
the the varangians
um I may be mixing a couple of things up
but you can look it up if you're
interested so the history of the of the
ruse people the Russian people goes back
about a thousand years their actual
original capital was Kiev yes most and
then there was this period uh which uh
essentially was the Russians coming
under the Mongol yolk after the deaths
of the great conqueror SRI chingas Khan
his sons decided to conquer territory
just for the heck of conquering yeah and
then Russia came under the Yoke of the
Mongols led by their great generals
the the great Mongol General subodhai
the Valiant who began his career career
under Genghis Khan and later on uh he he
uh served the Second Great Mongol Khan
so the Russians came under the Mongol
yoke it was a very tough time for them
yes and then the Mongol Empire
disintegrated uh rather soon sooner than
one would have expected but that's what
happened then eventually moscovy became
a thing and then the Russian Empire
became a thing I'm really doing a fast
forward of a very large period of
history but then you had this period of
Russian expansion so during the time
essentially when the Europeans the rest
of the Europeans were were destroying
and colonizing Africa and the Americas
and mainly India where most of the
wealth came from
at that time the Russians were expanding
eastwards further eastwards for the
resource so if you look at the ethnic
groups who live in in in the eastern
non-european part of Russia you have
non-slavic people who live here uh you
have the the turkic origin Tatar people
the tatars and there was a large long
lengthy period of conflict between the
invading Russians and the indigenous
Tatar people of of what is now of
Siberia essentially a long extended
protracted period of conflict between
the Invaders and the people who were
defending their Homeland the the
the tasks the tatas are are turkic
people yeah today it's they are all
intermingled with the Slavic peoples and
all that and today I I suppose they most
of them speak Uh Russian as either a
primary language or a secondary language
um then you have the people of Tua then
you have the mongolic Mongol origin
people of Russia and you have various
tonguesic peoples and all that even the
I knew people north of Manchuria and and
in the sakhalian region the the
Kamchatka region and all that uh you
have Inuit origin people as well
so these are all conquered territories
right this enormous territory was all
conquered by an expansionist Russian
Empire and the Russian Empire even
conquered Alaska by the way and then
they sold it uh in the middle of the
19th century to the Americans because of
various geopolitical pressures they were
facing from the from their conflict
from their ongoing conflict with the
British Empire in Central Asia the
Crimean War all that yeah you can read
that it's it's a very complex uh
history that we are dealing with over
here
the truth is
the Russians did not have colonies the
Russians simply conquered this enormous
expanse of territory what's a colony
India was a colony of the UK of the
British of the English so Britain is all
the way over here this island west of
Europe This Island of the Atlantic Ocean
and they conquered India and they put in
they set up a government over here an
invasive oppressive uh occupying force
that
that administered India by force
forcibly and extracted every last bit of
of value out of India that is called
colonization and a similar thing
happened in various parts of Africa
various parts of various European uh
kingdoms and and Empires and and nations
colonized various parts of Africa Africa
was divided up between them and they all
proceeded to extract everything of value
Out of Africa and a similar thing
happened in the Americas as well of
course in the in the Americas you had
settler colonialism yes which means that
the Europeans actually conquered this
territory and settled down and and
genocided the natives yes that's a whole
different part of history and a similar
thing happened in South America I mean
in Argentina where are the natives today
none survive what about Chile Where are
the natives hardly any any survive at
all in Brazil also the the real natives
are all you know oppressed and all that
it's a it's a a very sad and terrible
history so that is settler colonialism
you take you you conquer a territory you
settle your own people there and you
essentially marginalize the inhabitants
who are native to the land that is
settler colonialism so when you talk
about Russia
this entire enormous expanse of
territory that's settler colonialism of
course today
in much of Eurasia the Eurasian part of
Russia the uh the principal ethnic
groups that you will find will probably
be of Tatar origin or tungusic origin of
or I I know origin or tuvan origin in
various other groups but they all come
under the Yoke of Russian culture and
the Russian language so the Russian
language is is the official language and
so on it's it's quite complex the whole
scenario but all of this is conquered
territory it is non-russian territory
non-slavic territory yeah it has all
been conquered reasonably recently
so the Russians are no uh
strangers to colonization and what they
have done in in the Eurasian part of
Russia the Asia Asiatic part of
present-day Russia is settler
colonialism yeah
so and the easternmost great city is
Vladivostok just north of North Korea it
is a port city that freezes in the
winter yeah
and uh it's it's quite close to Japan so
so Russia and Japan have this simmering
ongoing territorial dispute that dates
back more than a century dates back to
the major restoration
and maybe even before that if we go
deeper into it but that's the deal so
the question I I hope I've answered it
they
most of today's Russia is non-slavic
territory that has been conquered by the
Russian Empire that's what it is so
Russia itself is no stranger to
colonization to settler colonization and
Russia itself the present-day nation
state of Russia is the uh successor of
the USSR which itself was a successor of
the Russian Empire under which was which
was built by various uh
various uh rulers like uh Ivan the
Terrible uh
what was his name uh
Catherine the Great and so on I don't
yeah you know just a couple of names I
can tell you there's much more to it
Peter the Great and so on
so that's what it is so yes the Russians
also have had colonies they also have
indulge in colonization they are
actually not very different
from from their European neighbors yeah
and and if you want to know about about
the uh
about the the Tatar people for instance
let's do a quick Google search about the
tatars uh you may have heard of those
Russian siblings tennis playing siblings
siblings marath and the Nara marath and
the Nara safin
yes so both of them
they are siblings yes uh they are tennis
players they have both been world number
one they have both been Grand Slam
champions I don't think Dinara ever won
an individual Grand slamsa title but she
won at least a doubles titled at least
if I can if I remember correctly and she
was world number one and her brother
also was world number one
uh yeah so yeah obviously they don't
they don't look very happy here they
must have lost a match or something but
yes these two are these are siblings and
these are Tatar they belong to the Tatar
ethnicity
so there are many uh Russian uh
people permanent people who are tatars I
believe another one is
a gymnast yes
uh this gymnast she also has has a
turkic Tatar ethnicity mixed ethnicity
perhaps but definitely Tatar and so on
so that's the Tatar people who are a
major ethnic group a non-slavic ethnic
group within Russia and they are
conquered people by the way they are a
conquered people
they are originally turkic
yeah so that's a deal I hope I have
answered the question
Daniel Nicholson says you rightly
predicted a Chinese misadventure along
the LSC tawang do you see a possible
two-front War Western Theater via
Pakistan in the near future now that the
U.S China and Pakistan's interests
coincide like never before if the U.S
and China seek a bipolar World China
would at least for now wouldn't it be
the perfect time to thwart India's rise
look if there is a conflict in an actual
War see right now we have this uh low
kind of you could call it a low
intensity conflict along the Northern
India Tibet border right at various
parts of the border the Chinese try to
stir up trouble do these incursions the
salami slicing tactics that's what they
keep on attempting to do and all that
and from time to time you have clashes
like what happened in galwan which was
one of the worst clashes in a very long
time in living memory and of course the
more recent December 9 Clash
um near tabang in which the in in both
the clashes the Chinese came out worse
right uh so this is what you would call
a simmering border issue a very low
intensity conflict is it's not a war but
in case India and China actually do go
to war I expect that there will be two
front War immediately the moment India
and China go to war hypothetically if it
happens the pakistanis most likely will
also try and stir up trouble they also
may try to uh
uh do some kind of coordinated action
along with the Chinese and maybe perhaps
with U.S blessings yeah because nobody
wants India to to become too strong too
powerful uh so I believe that if there
is in the future a war between India and
China there most likely will be a
simultaneous war between India and
Pakistan as well so what India needs to
do
is Pakistan we have to be very clear
about how we're going to deal with it if
Pakistan and India go to war for
whatever reason India has to ensure that
the outcome of the war is decided within
the first five minutes of the war
that's it
the outcome of any future india-pakistan
War see that if there is a war between
India and Pakistan in the future it
should be the final war between between
India and Pakistan and India needs to
ensure that the outcome of this war is
decided within the first five minutes
that's it I need I need to say no more
apart from that
um so yes if the Chinese
play some kind of mischief and there
does
occur in India China war most likely
there will be a simultaneous India
Pakistan War as well Indian is to ensure
we
end the war within essentially the first
five minutes and it is very much within
our capabilities
to end the war to to make the outcome of
the war a foregone conclusion within the
first five minutes of the conflict we
have to be ready
24x7 for this eventuality
um
so yes once we do that we can deal with
the Chinese at our Leisure we have
significant advantages in the Himalayas
the Chinese whatever the so-called
strengths are they are nullified by the
by the Himalayan terrain they they are
well physically not very
um
very impressive specimens first of all
the Chinese yes as we can see uh in all
these videos that come out of various
clashes between the Indian and Chinese
forces we cannot ever
underestimate them but we have
significant advantages uh
so yes if there is a war in the future
whenever it is it's most likely going to
be a two-front war we have to ensure
that the moment the pakistanis decided
to start up trouble and and you know
initiate a conflict it should be the
last india-pakistan conflict and the
outcome should be decided within the
first five minutes of the conflict
that's it then we deal with China and
then the Chinese need to be taught a
lesson because see China is in is a
perennial threat for India as long as it
holds Tibet now Tibet is a is an issue
that we can deal with in the future I
think uh so that's that's what it is so
the Americans would definitely give
their blessings for for trouble with
India to the pakistanis at least yeah so
India needs to ensure that first of all
we don't want a conflict in the next
five ten years India needs to rise
Pakistan is now of assault state of the
U.S Chinese are their own they have
their own agenda so we need to find ways
to counterbalance all of this you know
we can counter balance the Chinese with
the Russians the Russians also fear the
Chinese they also don't trust the
Chinese we need to utilize that to our
advantage and work constructively
together with Russia for our mutual
benefit similarly the Iranians don't are
scared of China
oh I'm sorry the Iranians uh they fear
Pakistan
at the on the eastern border a
nuclear-powered U.S basal State at
Iran's border it's a nightmare for Iran
it's a nightmare
so we need to leverage that as well
against Pakistan so these are the things
we need to do but in the future if there
is a war
and it it turns into a two-front war we
know what to do and I'm sure the Indian
army knows more than me what needs to be
done yeah so yeah that's a deal
akhil says Dear Sir can the Agni 5
rocket be used to proper satellites into
space is the fuel that's used in the
pslv the gslv ETC and the Agni missiles
is the fuel different when it comes to
these missiles and and and and the GSL
EPS will be uh family of rockets how are
these Rockets similar or different so
first of all missiles are Rockets yeah
missiles follow the same uh physics
physics laws they operate on the same
principles as uh is a commercial rocket
does like the GSL or the pslv or the or
the certain five missile or the or the
SpaceX Falcon missiles or the Russian
missiles the Russian Rockets or the
Chinese Long March Rockets these are all
Rockets
so
what we call missiles ballistic missiles
they actually are nothing but Rockets
yeah but we call them missiles because
they are it's it's a techn it's a
terminology we use because those are the
missiles are used for military purposes
and what we call Rockets are used for
scientific and Commercial and other
purposes the space exploration and
things like that now what is the
difference
can the Agni 5 missile the it's which is
most likely an InterContinental
balancing missile
can that missile be used to proper
satellites into space absolutely it can
yes the question is why don't we do it
then right why don't we use the these
missiles so first of all we don't want
the Agni 5 missile to be very visible
when you launch a piece or GSL where the
whole world can see it it can be tracked
all its flight characteristics can be
studied in all that we need the Agni 5
and other ballistic missiles to remain
under wraps and remain secret and
whenever we test them we're going to do
a low atmosis you know not a very not
big enough we're going to keep the
altitude low and all that we cannot do
certain things to
to prevent the world from from unknowing
too much about it so that's number one
so we can use missiles like the Agni 5
to launch satellites but we don't want
to do that the other thing is that there
is a difference in the fuel that's uh
for instance the the gslv and the pslv
they will most likely have they are
multiple stage Rockets
there will be a solid state somewhere in
there but the main cryogenic stage will
be a liquid fuel stage there will also
be a stage with hypergolic fuels yes
what are hyper what is hypergolic fuel
it's it's like two different chemical
liquid chemicals that if you bring them
together they will spontaneously ignite
Now liquid fuels have an advantage over
solid fuels
liquid fuels have a much higher specific
impulse as compared to solid fuels
liquid fuels are engines that use liquid
fuels are much more efficient they
produce much more thrust than engines
that use solid fuels the other thing
about liquid fuels is that if you have a
rocket that's that is that uses liquid
fuels you can shut it down and restart
it you can throttle it up you can
throttle it down so you can you have
much more uh flexibility as to how
you're gonna use the rocket when you
have a rocker with solid fuel you cannot
shut it down you cannot restart it you
cannot throttle it up you can throw it
you cannot throttle it down once it is
ignited it's gonna stay ignited until
the whole solid fuel is used up like in
your firecrackers and all you have these
Rockets you once you ignite it it's gone
it's it's not gonna stop until the fuel
is gone right so that's how it is so
that's the difference between so so your
ballistic missiles like the ugly five
Etc they use solid fuels why do we use
solid fuels for these missiles it's
because we need to store this massage
for a long period of time maybe for
years in canisters and all that you
can't do that with liquid fuels but with
solid fuels you can do that for instance
if you have a rocket with little which
uses a liquid hydrogen and liquid oxygen
that you cannot keep it in a container
for years the container will will blow
up yeah because metal suffers fatigue
and these liquids are under high
pressure and very low temperatures you
have to maintain that at very low
temperature it's not possible to do that
indefinitely yeah so these are the
differences uh
so mainly and and in in a rocket like
the pslv or the gslv or or even in a
system like the space shuttle which is
now retired you had a combination of
liquid fuels and solid fuels for
instance if you look at the Space
Shuttle let's put the space shuttle on
the screen
space shuttle
one second here is here it is
you look at the space shuttle
uh this is the space shuttle you see
that uh the the main uh bird the main uh
aircraft spacecraft is attached to this
orange orangish enormous fuel tank and
it has two rockets on the sides yes so
the two rockets on the sides are
boosters I I believe the the the they
are ignited only for like 90 seconds or
two minutes or so these are solid fuel
boosters they provide a very quick and
dirty thrust initially and then they are
jettisoned and and the main engines are
also ignited at the same time in the
very beginning and they use fuel liquid
fuel from this enormous orange tank so
you have a system that uses solid as
well as liquid fuels here and similarly
in the gslv I believe there is a stage
with with
the gslv has booster Rockets as well
booster Motors I believe those are
liquid fueled booster models but there
is a solid fuel stage also I believe in
the gslv if I'm not mistaken can you or
maybe in the pslv I have not studied
this in great depth but that's how
typically it works so a rocket can use
multiple kinds has multiple stages and
you could have a solid fuel stage as
well so that I hope explains the
difference between solid fueled rockets
and liquid fuel Rockets uh solid fuel
Rockets are solid fueled engines are
typically used in military
ballistic missiles because you need to
store them for long periods of time you
can certainly launch Satellites with
them but you don't want to do it
because first of all it's it's a
it's more costly and secondly you want
to keep that rocket that the missile all
its characteristics Under Wraps you want
to keep it classified you want to keep
it secret you don't want the world to
know much about it that's the reason why
it it is the way it is
all right
needy says cruise missile doesn't have
unlimited range and no missile is
nuclear powered they just carry nuclear
warheads or payload I think this is in
response to something I had said and I I
had said that the Russians have
a nuclear-powered cruise missile that
has an essentially unlimited range so in
response to that my dear friend akhil is
saying that cruise missiles don't have
unlimited range and no missile in the
world is nuclear powered please
understand you're wrong
okay am I wrong
I I don't get this man let's let's do
this
um
I'm gonna have to do it sorry
here we are this is an article from 2018
Russia reveals Unstoppable nuclear
powered cruise missile
yes
Putin announced a new high yield
InterContinental range cruise missile
perpet purportedly capable of
penetrating any missile defense system
yes what does it say here
it's a cruise missile which has
essentially unlimited range read the
article and it will tell you that it has
essentially unlimited range it is
powered by a nuclear motor
all right it is a nuclear-powered
missile
it is called the 9M 730
yes it's a Russian nuclear-powered
nuclear-armed cruise missile under
development it has an essentially
unlimited range
and I also spoke I think about nuclear
ramjets and all that yes you can have a
nuclear-powered Ramjet engine you can
even have a nuclear powered scramjet
engine I'm gonna not gonna go into that
right now but there you are so my dear
friend akhil you took the time to type
this comment it must have taken you 10
20 seconds in the same time you could
have done a Google Search and disabused
yourself of your notion that this that
there are no unlimited rage cruise
missiles or nuclear Powers I just don't
get this attitude that so many people
have that what I know is the is the
ultimate truth
how can you be so certain about it
how long did it take me to to show that
that this actually is the case this
unfortunately you know reminds me of
what Bertrand Russell said I don't need
to be I don't mean to be disrespectful
to a Kill but the problem the problem
with the world is that fools and
Fanatics are always completely certain
of themselves and wiser people are full
of doubts
so I'll kill my friend over here is
completely certain of himself that
cruise missiles don't have unlimited
range and and missiles can never be
nuclear powered how can you be so
certain of yourself
a simple Google search which takes
hardly 5-10 seconds will show you that
it is indeed the case I just don't get
this attitude I just don't understand
how people have this attitude it is so
frustrating for me to see
so many Indians intelligent educated
Indians who have these this attitude
that I know everything
and if somebody tells me something which
which goes against what I believe then
that person is a fool
why are people so close-minded
it's like I I got my degree now I I my
education is done I have nothing more to
learn and the rest of my life I will go
around spouting yarn to people that's
the kind of attitude many Indians have
and I see that all the time I see it on
Twitter you tweet anything there are 50
people who come and jump at you and say
that you are you're wrong you're a fool
blah blah blah blah blah blah blah
um
I don't get it I just don't get it why
are people so close-minded why are
people so dogmatic why can't you be open
to learning why can't you be opal to the
possibility that maybe you don't
understand everything in the world and
maybe there is information out there
that out there that you have still not
come across why be like this I I don't
get it it is really frustrating for me
and this is a brilliant example of that
it took me 10 seconds to debunk what
this gentleman is saying
really really
ah frustrating for me to see this
anyway let's go somewhere else talk
about something else
um
Daniel says what are the geopolitical
implications of Russia potentially
cutting off gas supplies to Europe
should the U.S led waste exert pressures
beyond the Russian threshold Germany not
happy and all so and so forth the
geopolitical implication of Russia
cutting of gas supplies to Europe is not
that the Europeans will die of of
freezing or anything it's that Europe's
economy is gonna crash
excuse me so if the Russians cut off all
gas supplies to Europe the Europeans
will have no option but to acquire but
to but to purchase gas from the
Americans from across the Atlantic Ocean
and they are doing that right now
already and the Americans are forcing
the Europeans to pay three times the
price that the Europeans were bringing
to Russia to Russia for the same amount
of gas so the Americans are essentially
extorting incredible amounts of money
out of Europe
now when
energy becomes so incredibly expensive
first of all it's gonna cause incredible
hardships to the
ordinary man woman and child the
families the population their energy
bills will essentially triple or
quadruple it's going to become
unaffordable for some people to to warm
their houses in the winter in India in
in much of India in the winter you just
wear a sweater or something like that
you don't need to heat your house unless
you're in Northern India in in
but in most much of India it's not
necessary in Europe you essentially
freeze to death if you don't have eating
in the house
so it's gonna be
very tough for many Europeans to just
afford
to pay the bills the the heating bills
that's number one secondly
much of
not much of but all the entirety of the
European economy depends on the energy
Germany for instance is the Europe is
Europe's uh industrial Powerhouse
they manufacture all kinds of things if
you want to manufacture steel if you
want to manufacture cars if you want to
manufacture anything you need large
quantities of energy you need
electricity you need energy you want to
melt metal and make steel you need a
huge amount of energy to do that
and if energy because if the if your
energy builds triple or quadruple where
are you profits gonna come from
it's gonna destroy Europe's economy
it is going to essentially
de-industrialize Europe if this
continues over three to five years
that's the problem these are the
geopolitical implications of Russia
potentially cutting off gas supplies to
Europe the Russians could also cut off
uranium supplies to to various European
nations
France I think uh
60 I think of its energy comes from
nuclear power where is the uranium yeah
yeah where does the uranium fuel come
from
these are the problems so it's going to
essentially Europe it's going to
Europe's economy it's
Manufacturing in industrial uh prowess
and it's it's going to essentially make
Europe completely dependent on the
Americans completely right now at least
they have their economy they have their
manufacturing base they have their
industrial base yes once that is
crippled what will they do
that's the thing
so that's the game that's being played
um
Vladimir it says private from Russia
don't you think India should have long
ago achieved the economic targets and
should have crossed a 10 trillion dollar
Mark with Indians known to be the
smartest in the world where did Indian
policies go wrong Russian respect from
my to my Indian friends from
Russia private my friend so what
happened yes it is true that Indians
Indians do have this I mean in the past
Indians had this reputation of being the
smartest people in the world the
Japanese considered Indians to be the
smartest in the world Chinese also did
and so on so forth yeah
um so yes Indians are very intelligent
and smart people
um so what happened what happened is
that India had terrible leaders yeah
after 1940 what happened in 1947 is that
power was transferred from one set of
crooks to another set of crooks the
British who were occupying and ruling
India for more than 200 years and they
had totally destroyed and crushed
India's economy they then handed over
power to a set of Indian Indians who
essentially continued the same poetarian
practices and policies that the British
had instituted the same system persisted
they did not try to reform the system
the system of Oppression the system of
of of the colonial system that the
British had built the same system still
exists today
it's a deeply entrenched system because
now Indians believe it is their own
system yeah and the leaders let's take
the example of the shining example of
Shri the great Mr jawaharlal nehru
you know India's economy was so badly
broken that
even if you had okay policies not great
policies India's economy would have
grown at least 10 percent a year because
it was so badly broken just just to
restart it the growth would have been 10
plus per year
you take the example of Japan Japan was
totally devastated by by the Americans
in World War II and see how rapidly they
were able to emerge out of the ashes and
re-industrialize themselves India could
have done a much better job India had a
certain amount of infrastructure already
present which is the Japanese did not
have they had to rebuild everything from
scratch so it was terrible terrible
leadership that
ensure that India remained incredibly
poor
until very recently now India is totally
slowly Rising
From the Ashes now and India is now
becoming a significant power in the
world
but this could have happened in 1947
itself the process could have been
certain Motion in 1947 itself it is the
terrible leadership which the British
put in place
that
ensured that India did not achieve all
those economic targets yeah
until the 1990s India and China were the
same position economically and the
Chinese then took off
in India is now taking off
so we had the opportunity to to do that
in the 1940s 1950s itself and we lost
this these so many decades because of
these terrible leaders who were not
democratically elected by us they were
put into place and Indians were made to
believe that these are your leaders and
they represent you they did not
anyhow so that's that's what happened
right
Karman man says why is Canada a
prosperous Nation even though it has
only a population of 38 million Souls
what are your thoughts on the jtf 2 it's
said to be one of the most highly
skilled Special Forces groups behind the
Delta Squad in the British SAS you know
every nation has its own special forces
and all that uh the Indonesians have
their special force the Russians have
the spit snats uh the British of the SAS
the the Americans the Marines the
Indians have the Marco's and various
other groups and so on every nation
proclaims that our that its special
forces are the best so I don't think
there's anything significantly special
about the Canadian jtf2 I'm sure they
are competent and they are highly
skilled in all that but so are the
special forces of many other nations so
I don't I don't see anything special
about the Canadian jtf2 I am sure they
specialize in certain things which all
that now the other question is why is
Canada prosperous Nation even though it
has a population of 38 million
take a look at the map where is our map
take a look at Canada it lies north of
the U.S
it is an enormous territory larger than
the US so 38 million people occupy this
enormous resource-rich territory which
has no
geopolitical threats at all
it is
um a U.S was Hal state
it is under U.S protection
it has no other threats of of any kind
yes so no need to maintain a large army
a large a large Armed Force no need to
do any of that enormous amounts of
territory
all kinds of resources every resource
you can hope to have so why will it not
be prosperous
and the fewer people you have the more
prosperous you are of course of course
if you have just 20 people it's not
gonna work out but if you have 38
million that's plenty to to you know to
build as much Prosperity as you want so
it's all about the territory the
resources and the lack of threats that's
why Canada is so prosperous
yeah so that's the reason it's very
simple
giant Verma says I have watched Avatar
way back in 2010 2011. I hated most of
the humans in the Avatar movie because
all they do is plunder resources and do
other atrocities yes that's that's
storyline Jake Sully is the human who
becomes a blue guy yeah recently I
watched Avatar 2 the storyline is simple
but I realized that the West is actually
telling their own story the humans in
the Avatar movies are the Western
Nations and the indigenous blue people
the navi race are all the other
oppressed people of Earth the South
Americans the North American indigenous
people the Africans the Asians in
Australia well you have realized
something very interesting
if you watch Avatar one which I watched
when it first came out
um it is essentially a white savior
movie if you watch uh movies like The
Last Samurai in all these movies there's
this white guy who goes to a foreign
culture and there are elements of that
foreign culture that are really nice and
very very uh Noble in all that but
eventually it is shown that the white
guy has something Superior about him and
he eventually ends up saving saving the
day
so so this is this is called the white
savior Trope in in western movies so
Avatar essentially is a white savior
movie I I'm sure I can think of many
other examples but I give you one The
Last Samurai
um The Last of the Mohicans also could
be possibly a white savior movie
uh so Avatar is like that and yes
in the Avatar movie part one the humans
are the invasive species on this
wonderful uh Moon called tandoora where
the natives they live in in harmony with
nature yeah they they worship me there's
no worship system as such shown but they
kind of worship nature itself in the
form of what they what they call it Eva
or something yeah they worship nature
that the great mother they call it uh
the the divine feminine and these
Invaders the white guys
so that's how it is and Avatar 2 is also
about veiling and all that I recently
saw that yeah it's yeah
so essentially you are right James
Cameron has made these movies along
those lines that the humans that are
depicted in the Avatar movies are they
represent the uh European colonialists
and the blue guys the blue people the
the speed the indigenous species they
represent all the various non-white
native peoples of Earth now
if you watch the Avatar movies you will
see some people who have characteristics
of of African races in India on Earth
yes some people speak with it with uh
supposedly African accent and all that
uh some of the elements of culture that
are depicted among the navi are similar
to the Native American culture right yes
and some of some of the cultural
elements in the next in the second movie
reminding of Polynesian culture or Maori
culture right the the tattoos on the
face and the living of living in in
harmony with the ocean and all that
but they will never show any elements of
Indian culture
yeah you watch any Hollywood movie
western movie they will kind of uh
tolerate and to some extent respect
various indigenous cultures like if you
watch the the wakanda forever movie they
are extolling the glories of indigenous
African culture yes
there are various movies in which they
they show that Native American culture
is wonderful if you watch Moana they
they uh kind of celebrate Polynesian
culture Samoan culture all that have you
ever seen a western movie a Hollywood
movie A English-speaking movie
English language movie in which they
celebrate Indian culture you will never
see that they only celebrate the culture
the cultures of the peoples they have
defeated
you understand that
they only celebrate the culture
of the peoples they have defeated the
defeated people
Indians are not defeated yes we were
colonized by them but we have risen
again and we are rising
so they will not celebrate our culture
racism is okay in certain cases right
now it's okay to be racist against the
Russians and it's perfectly okay to be
Hindu phobic it's perfectly okay to be
openly hindophobic in in American
Academia in in English speaking in
Western Academia perfectly fine
but you can't be something else phobic
but you can be Hindu phobic this is the
hypocrisy of the West
and I I I need you all to realize this
right so avtar is a good example let's
say it's a good example so so nice of
giants to bring to to ask this question
says just check what Einstein thought of
Indians in Chinese so I think this is in
response to one of the one of the clips
that I put that I had put out about
Israel the India Israel relationship and
Indians lots of Indians worship Israel
blindly for whatever reason and uh so so
raghavender says just check what
Einstein thought of the Indians in the
Chinese so first of all Einstein was a
Jewish person for sure he was not
Israeli he was offered the
Prime ministership of Israel I believe
once and I think he he
refused that
he was definitely a Jewish person he was
born in Germany he then became a Swiss
citizen for some time and then he moved
to the U.S to Princeton so that's the
kind of life he had he was a Jewish
person he could have become an Israeli
citizen if he wanted he could have
become the prime minister of Israel if
he wanted uh so the question is what did
he think of Indians in Chinese is a good
question to ask yes
let's find out what Einstein thought of
the Indians in the Chinese yes yes let's
see
uh Einstein's travel Diaries or if we
reveal shocking xenophobia this is from
a British
uh publication called The Guardian it's
it's always been anti-india but here it
is
so private journals kept by the
scientists and humanitarian icon show
prejudiced attitudes towards the people
he met while traveling in Asia so I
don't think he ever
came to India but he did pass through
Sri Lanka and so the attitudes towards
the people of Sri Lanka will be the same
as the attitude towards Indians at that
time I believe that he thought of the
Sri Lankans as Indians because Sri
Lankans of course are ethnically
culturally are Indian
um so what is he right in China the man
who famously once described racism as a
disease of white people describes the
industrious filthy obtuse people he
observes he knows how the Chinese don't
sit on benches while eating but squat
like Europeans do when they relieve
themselves out in the leafy Woods
even the children are spiritless and
look of dues yes after earlier writing
about the abundance of Offspring and the
fecundity of the Chinese he goes on to
say it would be a Pity if these Chinese
supplant all other races for the likes
of us the mere thought is unspeakably
dreary yes
so that's what he thought about the
Chinese
uh
what does it say
um he went through various Nations
he he saw he wrote about the Chinese
that even those reduced to working like
horses never give the impression of
conscious suffering means the Chinese
essentially enjoy suffering A peculiar
herd-like Nation
often more like automatons or robots
than people
uh
uh I noticed how little difference there
is between men and women really Albert
Einstein what are you saying
and I don't understand what kind of
Fatal Attraction Chinese women possess
which enthralls the corresponding men to
such an extent that they are incapable
of Defending themselves against the
formidable blessing of offspring
incredible yeah in Colombo in Ceylon
in Sri Lanka Einstein writes of how the
locals locals live in great filth and
considerable stench at ground level
adding that they do little and need
little the simple economic cycle of Life
what about the Japanese
um
Japanese unostentatious decent
altogether very appealing pure Souls Etc
um
and so on and so forth he is unable to
understand how Chinese men find their
women sufficiently attractive to have
Offspring with them that's incredible
so racist and dehumanizing and so on
yeah so that's what he wrote over here
and there's more did Einstein believe
that Indians were stupid his Diaries
suggest so uh what did he say what did
he say Indians Einstein believed seem to
have believed were biologically inferior
and were hampered by the subcontinent's
climate
that prevented them from thinking
backward or forward by more than a
quarter of an hour
Einstein believed that Indians are
incapable of thinking forward or
backward
by more than a quarter of an hour
incredible yeah
and this is the guy who attached his
name to the Bose statistics they are now
called Bose Einstein statistics yeah
um
Einstein came across Indians in Colombo
during his Far East voyage and he
mentioned their existence by referring
to their primitive lives
um
an attitude that uh all that here
geographical determinism and the Indians
alleged intellectual inferiority
Einstein attributes the alleged stoicism
of the Indians he encounters to
geographical determination by asking
wouldn't we too in this climate become
like the Indians
so Einstein a Jew who was forced to flee
Nazi Germany in the face of anti-Semitic
persecution
uh and so on he may have changed his
views on Race later in life he may or
may not we don't know he has shown no
uh no evidence of having done that yeah
so um yes so
that is indeed what Einstein thought of
the non-white people the Indians the
Chinese I'm I'm not sure what he said
about the Africans I have not gone into
that I I'm a little scared to look into
that actually yeah so yes
Einstein who is considered to be a
humanitarian a humanitarian icon
I
I'm sure he did not win the Nobel Peace
Prize but he is considered to be kind of
a saint because he opposed the the noble
the the atomic bomb which he helped
develop and all that
but yeah there you are
he clearly if you read his Diaries there
is clear evidence of of racist uh
attitudes and beliefs and the belief
that Indians are inferior and primitive
and incapable of thinking forward or
backward by more than a quarter of an
hour and the Chinese also are
unattractive and the women are very
hardly different from men and God knows
what else yes yes
so like I have said
see first of all racism I am sure is
prevalent in almost all ethnicities All
Nations and all that so we should not
take someone like Einstein to be
representative of the average Jewish
person I'm sure there are lots of Jewish
people who are not racist I'm sure there
are lots of Jewish people who don't have
prejudicial attitudes towards non-white
people the majority of the Jews are
actually non-white but we know what
happens in Israel and so let's go not go
into that right now but yes uh to this
point it is indeed true that Einstein
was
had these deeply racist attitudes
towards the people of India and China
that is uh the sad truth
this is a long question Ajay says about
the mrfa program multi-role fighter
aircraft do you think that instead of
biting buying all 114 factors of the
same type we should diversify the deal
and by say 38 fighters of the rafale 38
f21s 35 su-35s 38 to 35s recent events
have shown that it's not wise to totally
rely only on one country for anything
or is diversifying too expensive in
terms of Maintenance I'm asking the 78th
time so hopefully it will get accepted
okay
um
when you see India has how many
different kinds of fighter planes does
India have we have the almost obsolete
definitely obsolete mig-21s we have
mig-29s we had other migs also in the
past we have the the Jaguar fighter
plane we have the Mirage 2000 we have
the assault Rafael we have the Sukhoi 35
we have a whole Menagerie a whole zoo of
various different kinds of aircraft we
also have
the the
Poseidon aircraft the Boeing position
aircraft we have the the reaper drones
or some variant of that that I spoke
about yesterday we have a variety of
Russian transport planes American
Transport planes it's an incredible die
incredible diversity it's a it's a whole
menagerie of aircraft that we have in
the armed forces it is a logistical
nightmare to procure spare parts and to
have engineers in mechanics who are who
specialize in the maintenance and repair
of one kind of aircraft if you have 17
different kinds of aircraft you have to
have different 17 different types of
mechanics who specializes in this one
aircraft you can't have one mechanic who
does everything it doesn't work like
that it is a nightmare to have lots of
different kinds of aircraft
ideally we should have our own
indigenously manufactured aircraft so
that you know it it keeps things simple
now in case we go ahead with the mrf fa
program we should not diversify it will
be a it will be an additional nightmare
we should buy only one type of aircraft
keep things simple so that we can
procure the spares from one place only
hopefully manufacture the space pairs
in-house if if possible yeah
so that's how it should be it it doesn't
make any sense logically to to to split
it up into like four or five different
segments and first of all the F21 is
never going to be sold to India the
Americans won't ever do that the rafale
I think see the
you cannot really trust the Americans
with spare parts you when they feel like
they may they may cut off spare parts to
you or they may even remotely disable
the aircraft they've done this in the
past to various people they've done it
even to their to their five eyes partner
in Australia
in the 1980s late 80s the sold uh fa-18
fighter planes to the Australians and
when the Australians acquired the
fighter planes they realize that the
fighter planes are essentially disabled
they cannot acquire targets that the
Australians want them to acquire they
will only acquire targets lock onto
targets the Americans allow them to lock
onto it was a nightmare for the
Australians it's only in the 2000s more
than 20 years after they acquired the
aircraft that they were able to
circumvent this issue
so you cannot trust the Americans with
this the Russians have never done that
to India
um so maybe a Russian plane if the
Russians have a good one right now it
doesn't look like they have one so most
likely I would say that we should go for
the rafale and by if we are going to buy
a bunch of 114 planes maybe we should
just buy it by the Rafal because the
Rafal is one of the best fourth
generation fighter out there it is a
multi-road fighter plane it's a very
very comparable fighter plane and the
French overall are more reliable and
trustworthy than the Americans yeah
and they obviously would like to break
free of the shackles that they are under
the Masala the vasal state shackles uh
of the US so yeah so I would I would say
that it makes
imminent sense to just buy one type of
aircraft the mrfa program
okay descendant of rigvedic Clan says
please do talk about rigvedic Clans in
detail you have not explained this topic
in detail all right let's talk about
Rigby clams now
how do we talk about everybody Clans
from what period we have to since we are
talking about the rig Veda let's talk
about one of the oldest events that's
that's mentioned in the rig Veda which
is the first known geopolitical conflict
the first known war
it's called a battle the battle of the
ten things so let's take a look at what
srikanth talagiri has written about this
because
his writings are really good and it's
it's a great way of taking a look at
this so what did what has shrikant
palagari written about this and it's
it's in his writings that we can find a
listing of the various Clans so here we
are
the battle of the Ten Kings India's
Earth the world's earliest uh record of
a historical battle and it's
International repercussions so um so
there's a whole preliminary uh
explanation of various things over here
pretty Buddhist India obviously it's pre
Buddhist India and all that
um
so
there are various uh battles you know
the bad the
uh Hari up battle the battles of sudas
one two Etc let's talk about the
opponents that sudas that Kings had so
uh first of all who was sudas
um
sudas was a bharata puru king he
belonged to the Bharat puru Clan they
lived mainly in the kurukshetra area of
haryana
talagari uses the term tribe which is so
wrong
these are not tribes these are Clans a
tribe is a small grouping of primitive
humans who lived who lives in isolation
from other Human Society the rigvedic
clans were not tribes they were Clans so
this is a wrong term that he has used
but that's fine his scholarship is
excellent apart from this one um flaw
that we find
so uh
the
so so King so that's what the was the
king of the bharata puruklina who are
the opponents
that he was up against let's take a look
at that the Eastern opponents of sudas
so um
the enemies in the Eastern battles are
the Veda Clan the adjust the sigurus and
the yakuz
devaka manyamana
the Machi later became a great
mahajanapada right
uh and the purus as well so that's one
bunch of Eastern Clans now let's take a
look at a different set of Eastern clans
of the Rigby era
foreign
so these are the names that are
mentioned over here
these are people who lived in the east
of India clients that lived in the east
of India in the rigvedic age the Western
opponents of King sadas the dasas the
prithus or the parthavas the purses of
the parshwas yes or the simus the brigus
the alinas the paktas the balanas the
shivas the vishnes
foreign
these are a bunch of Western Clans there
are more
the shimu the Dasa the way karna these
are mainly in present in Afghanistan you
have the visioning which became the
nuristani of the peshachin clan the
paktun or the bhakta clan who are the
ancestors of today's bhaktus
uh then we have the Shiva Clan the Dasa
Clan the Alina and the shimu clan we
also have the brigus the Dasa the alinas
who became the Hellenic peoples the
brigus became the briggles became the
parthians the the phrygians
uh the the Dasa become the dacians the
shimyu
Osa
the later Iranians and so on
do we have more Western Clans the
suckers and all that that's later on
and so on
so then you have a description of the
battle let's take a look at this
different article
um
so yeah so it's a whole listing of Clans
that were expelled out of India as a
result of this battle
the shimu the Dasa
the vishnin the pakta who became the
pactoons
the balana who became the Bolan or
baluchi people the parthwa who became
the parthians of later times the Parsha
who were the ancestors of the Persians
yes the mudra or the media or the
medians the Shiva or the horizmians
that are mentioned in various European
uh texts the Alina or the Allens the
ancestors of the Iberian peoples
Spanish peoples the shimu or the
sarmatians the brigo or the or the
phrygians the Dasa or the dacians the
Alina who are the ancestors of the
Hellenic people the Greeks
the shimu and so on so this is a listing
of the various Clans that took part in
the the Great War that is known as the
battle of the Ten Kings there are
obviously lots of other clans that did
not participate in the war but I I would
say that this gives us a good example
of the number of Clans we had in
northern and western India and also
parts of Eastern Eastern India and the
kind of diversity that we had and this
was a major geopolitical event that
essentially shaped the the a lot of the
subsequent history of Eurasia because
all of these various Clans they had to
escape and go into Exile out of India
permanently and they went essentially
westwards and northwards and they
populated
uh push up the populated Greece they
populated the Balkans they populated the
the the the Central Asian regions and so
on so forth they essentially
they essentially spread Indo-European
language and culture across Eurasia West
or and north of India so that is in
brief about uh some of the rigvedic
Clans I cannot go into great detail
because then it will take a much longer
uh session but yeah that I hope gives uh
some kind of throw some kind of light on
this
okay akanda Bharat says
um yes thank you sir how advanced was
Queen vishpala's prosthetic leg from the
rig Veda do you believe high-tech
prosthetic limbs existed in Bharat
thousands of years ago let me answer the
second part of the question first do I
believe high-tech prosthetic limbs
existed in Bharat thousands of years ago
I don't think so
I don't think we had articulating limbs
with with you know fingers with
artificial fingers that you could use
like in like in The Terminator movies or
various other science fiction moves and
all I don't think there were high-tech
Advanced prosthetic limbs in India with
the mechanical elements and computer
computerized elements no absolutely not
this is thousands of years ago we why do
I say this because there is no evidence
of it you show me evidence from the
archaeological record I will change my
opinion because I have never seen any
evidence of any such thing that's why I
say that it is highly unlikely that you
had high-tech prosthetic limbs thousands
of years ago in India in Bharat right
now the question is how advanced was
Queen vishpala's prosthetic leg from The
Whisper from the rigveda so let's take a
look at what the rig Veda has to say
about this
yeah
so uh when it comes to the rigveda it's
a vishpala queen vishpala is mentioned
in a number of hymns let's put that on
the screen this is a English translation
of the rigveda this is hymn number 116.
the ashwins if you look at the 15th
verse or stanza whatever you want to
call it it says he gave vishpala a leg
of iron that she might move what time
the conflict opened so it mentions a leg
of iron it doesn't go into detail in
describing what this leg of iron look
like it says that vishpala was given a
leg of iron so that she could move when
the conflict happened which means that
she was able to resume the conflict and
she was able to fight with this uh iron
leg it's it's called a leg of iron let's
see what this section of the rig Buddha
says this is 118
him 118 ashwins
it says the quail from her great misery
he delivered and a new leg for vishpala
provided so it says a new leg over here
it doesn't say iron leg it says a new
leg
now let's take a look at uh hymn number
39 ashwin's
it says ye rescued Vandana and raised
him from the pit and in a moment gave
vispala power to move which means that
she was incapacitated because she lost a
leg and then she was given the power to
move so it doesn't go into any specifics
as to what kind of prosthetic limit was
all it tells us is that she was given an
iron leg
that's all we know
yes
so that's what we know that's the
evidence that we have from the text
itself from the Rigby itself of course
there are different various translations
you can take a look at the various
translations that we have there are
three four different English
translations there are translations into
Hindi and various other languages if you
want to go deep into it you can take a
deep dive and take a look at what it
says in all these various different
translations but what it tells you is
that she was given an iron leg and she
was able to go back into battle and she
was able to move again that's all it
tells you it doesn't tell you that it
was a fully articulated articulating
limb or it was made of carbon fiber with
with the artificial intelligence or any
such thing it says it was an iron limb
that's all we know and we have to go by
the evidence
that's it
that's the answer
okay they just says in Old Times how did
Kings and administrate and
administrators get updates on things
that were happening in Their Kingdoms as
India is a huge country and modes of
Transport were slow and traveling across
India must have taken months and months
and months
interesting question how did
um how
were Communications done in Ancient
India let's say let's talk about 2000
years ago during the uh kushan times or
maybe two and a half thousand years ago
during the morning times
how
were Communications done how did Kings
and administrators get get updates as to
what was happening in far off distant
parts of their empire Kingdom
let's take a look at the map of India to
get a better idea of what we are
talking about so here we have India now
let's take the example of Emperor Ashok
for instance he was one of our greatest
Emperors he when he was a prince not yet
the emperor he was the governor of
gandar his father had appointed Prince
Ashok as the Emperor of gandar gandar is
essentially the Pakistan Afghanistan
region yeah
uh during the the kushan times Peshawar
was one of the capitals of India
Peshawar is essentially part of gandar
and Kabul is the main capital it was
then called kapisa or something it was
also the capital of gandar so most
likely Ashoka was the governor in the in
one of these places either Peshawar or
Kabul or whatever was the then capital
of gandar
and his father obviously was in partly
Putra which is present-day Patna what is
the difference the the distance between
let's say Patna and Kabul
let us see from here to here that's
1820 kilometers in a straight line as
the crow flies yes but obviously if you
want to travel from Kabul to Patna
partly Putra you can't travel in a
straight line so it's gonna be more like
two and a half thousand kilometers now
in those days we had this great highways
and all that
these ancient great highways that that
uh
connected various parts of India so you
could travel along the great uttarapath
from partly Putra all the way to gandar
and that's what typically would do so
let's say the distance is by Road two
and a half thousand kilometers now let's
say uh Prince Ashok wants to send a
message
a report a status report let's say to
his father bindusar in partly Putra how
long will this take so let's say you
have a distance of two and a half
thousand kilometers and let's say it's
an Urgent Message so you send a
messenger on a horse and along the
uttarapata you will have these Imperial
rest houses base stations where you will
get fresh horses and let's say Ashok
tells the messenger don't stop until you
reach my father and send this message
now how fast does a horse typically run
let's let's assume roughly it's it's 40
kilometers per hour yeah and let's say
that the the messenger has access to
Fresh Horses every
every every two hours let's say so the
horse will travel let's say assume it at
40 kilometers per hour throughout and
let's say the messenger travels on his
horse 10 hours per day so in a day he's
gonna be able to cover 400 kilometers
along the uttara path
400 times
5 is 2000 so it will take about six days
six six and a half days for the
messenger on an urgent errand
to travel from Kabul
I am obviously oversimplifying but this
is the back of the envelope rough
calculation which gives us a good idea
of how things would have been so if the
guy travels on his horse with access to
Fresh Horses and if he travels at 40
kilometers per hour 10 hours a day then
the guy will be able to travel from
Kabul to partly Putra in less than a
week's time
yeah
and for redundancy you send three
different Messengers in case one of them
is not able to do for to travel very
fast the other guys will do it
so clearly
it will not take months and months and
months to send messages across India
across the entire enormous expanse of
India from gandha to patliputra within a
week you can send a message and
similarly from partly to to maybe
Southern India or wherever else so it
was not that slow yeah and that's why uh
people you know great Emperors were able
to have these enormous Kingdoms in India
chandragupta had a large empire Ashok
had the largest uh he he took the
mauryan Empire to its largest extent
that's what Ashoka did later kanishka
had an even larger Empire which which
touched the shores of the Caspian Sea
and the RLC it also Incorporated large
parts of xinjiang yes
um and obviously uh
uh gandar and so on so there also you
would have proper systems of
transportation and communication then
you had the Gupta Emperors you had a
literature who had a large empire and
all that so all these Empires would have
had proper systems of communications and
I would say that within the subcontinent
from gandhar to patliputra and from
north to south it would not take more
than more than a week for for
information to flow from one ex from one
extremity to another so that's how it
was done what would typically be on
Horseback you would have dedicated
Messengers couriers who and you would
have these long highways
Etc and various other networks of roads
and highways and you would have Imperial
Way stations along the way where you
would get fresh horses on demand and so
on and the highways would be very well
maintained yeah so the so-called grand
trunk road which Suri is alleged to have
built it was not he who built it he
simply refurbished
the uttarapatha that was in existence
for thousands of years
so that's how it was done so it did not
take months it would take hardly a week
for messages to go across
all right
um
arpit says I have seen many times that
that Latin Americans especially in
Mexico and so on in videos and
documentaries that the native people who
live there still look somewhat like the
people from the region of Southeast Asia
of Eastern Asia
do you think there could be a
possibility of migration between these
regions in the past yes definitely 100
percent
if you look at the genetics of the
people of or between the if you look at
the genetics of the Native American
peoples whether it is in North America
or South America there is a significant
Affinity uh significant commonality
between them and the people of Eastern
Asia for instance if you look at the
Inuit people let's go to the map so the
Inuit people are also or supposedly the
Eskimo people the so-called Eskimo
people who are now called the Inuit
people they live in Alaska in Northern
Canada even in Greenland Etc
these people they are very similar
genetically to the people of Siberia and
Mongolia it is very well known it is
established genetically and again if you
look at the people of uh if you look at
the native people of North America and
even Southern America most of them they
have this this appearance that is that
is reminiscent of the Eastern Asian
people the Siberian people the the
tungusik people I knew people the
Japanese people the mongolic people the
Han
it's because of migrations yeah
so the dominant theory is that about 13
000 years before today when the Earth
was in the grip of the Ice Age
at that time the the bearing Strait was
frozen and over here also you the the
sea was frozen across so it was just a
matter of walking across so humans were
able to walk across from Siberia into
North America and then over several
Millennia they migrated downwards
southwards and eventually made their way
into South America and all that so that
is the dominant theory of how the
Americas were populated so clearly there
is a migration from Eastern Asia
Northeastern Asia but now new things
have come to light there are there they
have found a remains of ancient humans
in South America that date back more
than a hundred thousand years so that
it's it's so that becomes clear so it
becomes clear that there have been
multiple waves of migration into the
Americas and the story may not be so
simple and it's so linear the way it is
made out to be we also have the mystery
of the olmecs yeah let's take a look at
that the Olmec will make
heads
so it so the Olmec heads are found
mainly in
Mexico the region of Mexico if I'm not
mistaken these are enormous colossal
heads if you can see you can see how
large the head is compared with with
human beings yes and if you look at the
facial features of all these all Mech
heads they don't look Eastern Asian they
look African yes
if you look at these the facial features
of these enormous statues these these
heads it's very apparent that these
represent African facial features not
Eastern Asian facial features
uh so it raises the question as to who
these people were did people migrate
from Africa into these places into into
South America and Leave Behind These
mysterious
uh gigantic carvings
so uh the story is not quite clear
uh and that there has been deliberate
neglect of the history of of the Native
American people because because we know
that America whether it's North America
or South America it's stolen land it has
been stolen by the Europeans they have
essentially wiped out the natives and
they have taken over the territory as
their own settler colonialism and
genocide colonialism so they don't want
to go deep into the history of the
Native American people because then it
will become very clear that the natives
are the true true uh owners and
custodians of the land and they have the
real claim to the land so the the the
the policy is let's let's not dig deep
into this in North America in the U.S
especially they have destroyed dozens
maybe hundreds of Native American
archaeological sites just flattened them
very few such sites actually remain you
know
in South America we have lots of sites
and uh the situation is different there
but there also there is the same overall
status
so yeah that's that's the that's the
deal the story may be quite complex but
there is clear that it is clear that
there were waves of migrations at least
one wave of migration from Eastern Asia
into the Americas and that's why so many
Native American people in Mexico in Peru
in Chile
Etc maybe in Brazil as well definitely
in Northern North America as well the
Inuit people the Eskimo people the
illusion people Etc they all look like
Eastern Asian that's that's the reason
why it is so
did ancient India trade more with
southeast Asia than in the Arabian Sea
first of all it's not the Arabian Sea
it's it was called even the Arabs called
it the Indian Indian Sea yeah
uh so the correct name of the so-called
Arabian Sea is actually the the we could
you could call it the Sea of saurashtra
perhaps so anyway did India trade more
in Southeast Asia than in what is called
here the Arabian Sea because Indian
culture seems to have spread primarily
through trade in Southeast Asia but
didn't but the same doesn't happen
doesn't didn't happen in the Arabian
Peninsula or the coastal regions of
Eastern Africa and Madagascar what's my
take on this
um
so if you look at the culture
of Southeast Asia whether it is the
whether it is Indonesia Java Sumatra Etc
whether it is uh Thailand whether it's
Myanmar whether it is uh Cambodia
Vietnam Laos Etc even if you talk about
um even if you talk about China even if
you talk about Korea and Japan there are
very
visible very very unmistakable elements
of Indian culture that still survive yes
all across the region southeast Asia
Eastern Asia Mongolia China everywhere
if you go westwards you don't see much
of that
if you go to Eastern Africa
you will see that the cuisine
in Kenya in Mozambique in Tanzania
Somalia it looks very Indian they use
the same spices they use turmeric they
use this same Indian spices the food
smells very Indian it looks and tastes
very Indian but it also also has a
distinctive African elements if you look
at the the textiles that ladies wear in
Tanzania Kenya Somalia
those textiles are very strikingly
similar to the textiles that that used
to be manufactured in Gujarat in the
17th 18th 19th century centuries you
know
um if you look at the style of dress in
the the dressing style of ladies in in
let's say Somalia uh Somalia ladies
uh what traditional
dress let's see what it looks like
this is the ladies traditional dress in
Somalia this is the sari you could
be forgiven for thinking that this is a
form of the sari
um what about Ethiopia
Ethiopia
the Ethiopian dress is not that it is
more Semitic or something but uh
you do see some some elements of the
sari or Indian dress in there as well
uh and the people of Ethiopia look kind
of Indian the people of Somalia also
look kind of Indian so
so then what's the deal right that's the
question uh
so going back to the map once again
it is known that Indians have had a
presence in Africa that dates back at
least four thousand years
because of the presence of zebu cattle
the Indian origin cattle which uh isn't
there they are they are known to have
existed in Egypt for dating back at
least 2000 BC and so on so Indians have
had a very long presence in Eastern
Africa
and you see that in the culture in
Eastern Africa you see that in the music
of Somalia and in other various parts of
Eastern Africa you see it in the
textiles the dressing style the cuisine
all these things but
so that's it it's so the Indian culture
is present but it's like an undercurrent
and why is it so and of course if you
look at the people of Yemen
let's take a look at the people of Yemen
yeah many people
the many people what do you many people
look like
so many people look like a mixture of
Arabs and Africans and Indians
so you will see people of African
appearance you will see people who look
very Indian
um
yeah it's a tragic story there so
so it's clear that uh and even if you
look at the people of Saudi Arabia or
Oman
Etc you will see this definitive Indian
features in their faces even if you look
at someone like Saddam Hussein he kind
of looks Indian right in in Mesopotamia
Iraq
so the thing is that Indians had very
old very long-standing and very deep
contacts and ties with Eastern Africa
with the Arabian Peninsula and so on but
then something happened
it was the Arabic imperialism that wiped
out Indian culture from all these
regions
and it uh replaced the Indian culture
with the Arabic culture and religion
that's what's happened there was this
devastating
slave trade that the Arabs carried out
in Africa
um which was horrific which which nobody
speaks about we know that the Europeans
devastated in Africa the Europeans did a
lot of slave slavery slavery practices
in Africa but the Arabs did even worse
than that and that's something no one
speaks about you speak you speak to
various Scholars about it they will say
that the Arabs used Africa for for
procuring labor labor they will use the
euphemism labor instead of instead of
slavery
uh that's how it is so what happened is
that there was
a very long-standing and very deep
Indian presence in Eastern Africa and
you will still find that in the genetics
of the people of Eastern Africa in Kenya
Tanzania Mozambique in Somalia
especially in Eritrea and in in Arabia
as well Oman Yemen Saudi Arabia it's all
been wiped out by Arabic imperialism so
that's why you see hardly any Indian
culture left
in East Africa and in the Arabian
Peninsula I would suggest why don't you
try and listen to Somalian music the
music of Somalia it sounds very Indian
you will see very definitive Indian
undercurrents in the in the music style
and so on in the Veda Singh and all that
so it's still visible to some extent but
it's now buried deep below the surface
and what's out there on the surface
exterior is the Arabic culture that is
all across the place so that's what
happened
right
um long question once again Surya
shekhar Panda says suppose the liberties
upon which a civilization is founded can
possibly be used as vulnerable
vulnerabilities with an intention to
destroy the civilization
if the civilization does nothing about
it its existence is in threat on the
other hand if it starts to regulate the
Liberties it's not the same civilization
anymore from the civilization's
perspective what is the solution to this
dilemma which is a win-win situation
from the perspective of the adversary so
let's talk yeah
multiculturalism uh cultural enrichment
Etc what they talk about in Europe yeah
so Europe over the past hundred years
has become very Progressive very liberal
yeah under the the shadow of the
American benevolence so Europe has a
certain kind of culture it's very it has
all these Liberties all these rights
that people have very open
um society and now you bring in people
from from the Middle East from Africa
who come from very different cultures
yes
and what it is alleged that these
immigrants they weaponize the Liberties
against the host nation so they say that
uh we're gonna use all these Liberties
to establish our presence in our our
culture in this nation and then we go
into eradicate your culture that that is
the allegation that is made
very often through from many quarters
some examples are France or other parts
of Europe and all that so the question
is that a very open culture
Europe is not a civilization Europe has
culture yes so he let's say you have a
culture with a lot of Liberties lots of
rights that people have all these rights
the right to free speech the right to
Pro to propagate your religion the right
to convert others and so on and so forth
you have the right
so these rights become vulnerable
vulnerabilities
when they are weaponized against the
host culture against the host nation but
if you curtail these rights then the
host culture loses its own identity it
is no longer the same thing it becomes
kind of intolerant what is to be done
what is to be done so we have to
understand that there are two sides to
every coin
you
should in a good culture and Society
have Liberties and rights
but those Liberties and rights
must come with duties and obligations
so yes you have Liberties you have
rights but you also have corresponding
duties and obligations
it has to be a balance otherwise you're
a society that's asking for trouble
and Indian Society always have this you
had rights but you also had duties you
had Liberties but you also had
obligations so let's say you have a
bunch of immigrants who come to your
land
and you offer them
you are magnanimous
you you offer them refuge in your in
your territory you give them a piece of
land to settle down in you tell them
you're free to to practice your culture
and so on
yeah you give them these Liberties and
rights but you also have to
explain to them what the duties are that
if you want to settle down in this land
you have to adopt our culture you can
keep on practicing your so take the
example of the zoroastrians The parsis
Who fled to India because they had
nowhere else to go
India was the old homeland of the
Persian people so at the end of the day
when the Arabs took over Persia and they
started massacring the inhabitants and
converting people by force those
pharsies those persons who wanted to
Safeguard their culture they decided to
escape to India and they they
came by boat or ship or whatever they
touched down on the western coast of
India in present-day Gujarat and the
local King told them that okay I I am a
magnanimous good guy I'm gonna give you
a piece of land a village to settle down
in if they called it sanjan or something
in Gujarat
you are free to practice your religion
we will not interfere with your way of
life
but
you have to adopt the local dressing
Style
you cannot so that's one thing you have
to dress like the locals and secondly
you have to adopt the language of the
locals as your own mother tongue so
that's how the parses became gujaratis
if you look at passes today if their
mother tongue is Gujarati you look at
Freddie Mercury foreign
or whatever but their actual mother
tongue and their actual culture is the
Gujarati culture and the Gujarati
language
and uh they would have had other duties
and obligations as well so in a social
in a
in a good Society in a robust Society
you it is perfectly fine to have
Liberties and rights but there also need
to be duties and obligations you cannot
be all rights and Liberties and no
duties I will take all the advantage
that I want but I have no obligation or
duty to the society it doesn't work like
that that is a society that is doomed to
fail
and that's what we are witnessing in the
west the Indian Society was very
different Indian civilization Indian
culture was built on the on the
foundation of what we call the dharmic
culture Dharma and in Dharma there are
very clear obligations and duties
and obviously today we are not
practicing that today is Indian Society
today's laws Constitution are all
adharmic
all Western in origin and that's where
most of India's problems originate today
it all dates back to the past Millennium
of humiliation which is something that
will need to be rectified in the coming
years
but that's how it is so yes
you should give people Liberties and
rights but those must be counterbalanced
by by requiring people to carry out
certain duties and having certain
obligations of society
so that's how a robot Society is
supposed to be people should have
Liberties people should have rights but
they also should have duties and
obligations that's how it goes
um unknown Nepali says if Russians don't
tolerate the failure of their leaders
then how come they did not Dethrone
Stalin when Operation Barbarossa made
Russia bleed a lot initially
when a country is in the middle of a Do
or Die life or death conflict
and you have a leader who is trying to
Keep the Country afloat
do you Dethrone him because he because
initially the war is going badly
that is what children would imagine they
would do
you dethron a leader after he has
conclusively failed in the conflict not
in the middle of a conflict
when you have a ship in a storm the
captain is doing his best to control the
ship it's taking on water it's not
capsized yet do you shoot the captain in
the middle of this that is
a guarantee that that's going to
guarantee that the ship will capsize
you don't do it in the middle of a huge
conflict yes
and the Russians knew what they were up
against
they knew how how powerful the Nazi war
machine was it was understood by
everyone that it's going to be a long
painful hard disastrous devastating
conflict and Russia will be really
fortunate if it survives this conflict
and everyone knew it's gonna cost a lot
in terms of blood oceans of blood
so
Stalin at the end of the day
he won
he ensure that is that his Red Army
entered Berlin before
the English speakers
and they are the ones who took out
Hitler's bunker right and possibly he
Hitler's body that's what is alleged we
don't know what happened
so at the end they won Stalin proved
that he was the Right leader initially
there were major setbacks the the Nazi
war machine the vermacht came up to the
outskirts of Moscow and from there they
were pushed back
um
they got bogged down in the rasputitsa
which I was talking about in past and
all that but the the the winter that
they suffered
the the all the devastation that they
suffered because of the winter was
punishment for their failure to use the
right
strategy there are the Germans so that's
what it was so yes Russians don't
tolerate failures but they will not
Dethrone a leader in the middle of a
conflict that is suicide
so please think from a more mature level
a conflict when it is ongoing you have
to support the leader
it's only when the the the outcome is
clear that you can take a call that's
how it goes you don't get rid of a
leader in the middle of a conflict that
is going to ensure that you're going to
lose the conflict
okay
says what is the obsession of humans
from all culture with pretty faces
how valuable are humans with pretty
faces
why
why do pretty faces attract so much
attention has it got something to do
with the nature of eyes or the Mind who
is considered pretty
uh I believe humans of all ages find a
certain kind of face attractive so it's
an evolutionary thing even if you show
what you call pretty faces to a
three-year-old child a toddler then they
will know they'll be able to distinguish
what from what is pretty from what they
would consider what is generally
considered to be not pretty so what
exactly is prettiness
prettiness I believe is about facial
symmetry both sides of the face are more
or less similar
and it's also about physical symmetry
it's not just about the face it's also
about the physique physical symmetry so
both sides should be symmetrical and the
thing about pretty face is what you call
Pretty Faces what we all call Pretty
Faces is spatial symmetry it's an
evolutionary thing it
if a person has good facial Symmetry and
good physical symmetry it is an
indicator that this person has good
genetics this person has Superior
genetic traits it is an indicator that
this person has access to good nutrition
that this person has most likely an
absence of any significant disease or
illness or any predisposition to illness
yeah uh it is an indicator an indirect
indicator of physical fitness of
survivability evolution is about
survival of the fittest so it indicates
that this person has a survival
advantage over others yeah it indicates
reproductive Fitness that this person
male or female will be able to produce
Offspring viable good strong healthy
Offspring it may also be possibly an
indicator of intelligence
so humans over thousands of years have
over hundreds of thousands of years have
evolved into face leaders at a glance we
can tell what does this face indicate to
us and typically it appears that you
know a properly symmetrical phase and
physique is indicative of all of these
good genetic and other traits
and in in
evolution in survival it's all about
finding the right partner so that you
can have healthy and strong Offspring
who will carry on the genetic lineage
that's what evolution is about so that's
why I believe humans are wired or
predisposed to find certain kinds of
faces and physics attractive which
indicates a whole range of other
uh characteristics that are not visible
that we may not think about when we see
a pretty face and you know it's
something that well I think it I'm I
don't mean to disrespect humans
by comparing them with other things but
you know even if you when you go to buy
fruits and vegetables you can tell by
looking at the fruit an apple or an
orange or a capsicum or a carrot whether
this this fruit is is
uh what quality it is you know so fruits
that are symmetrical and all you can
tell but just by one look that this this
is the right food to pick you know let's
say you're going to you've gone to pick
mangoes or apples
you see one and you know this is the
right one for me let me take this one so
that's all about you know take
understanding at a glance what the
quality is
in evolution it's about understanding
the quality of your potential mate or
partner yes and one of the indicators is
your facial Symmetry and physical
symmetry so that is most likely why
humans
um
like you say are obsessed with pretty
faces it's it's an evolutionary thing
um okay let's take some more questions
or did he says
okay Aditi says I want to ask I love a
person who is my friend but I don't know
how to approach him
I think he only thinks of me as a friend
please guide me
okay see uh you are assuming
that this person thinks of you as a
friend don't assume anything assumption
leads to problems you assume things
you're gonna end up in trouble or you're
gonna end up at a disadvantage you have
to make sure so if you think that this
person thinks of you only as a friend
go and talk to him
that's what I would say you know if you
want something in life
you go to act you have got to act you
will not get something unless you go and
take it or unless you go and ask for it
nobody is gonna give you anything for
free you have to go and ask for
something that you want
so if you love this person
and you see you you it's clear that
you're already friends so maybe this
person uh
cares for you yeah so in that case why
don't you go and ask that you know we
are friends but I have this kind of
this sort of feeling for you is it
something that you are
in a position to reciprocate do you feel
the same way or not it's fine yes or no
but let me know it's always the direct
approach is always the best approach and
it's not like girls should not do it
girls can also do it I have known girls
who did that so it's fine uh so
you have to understand that in life if
you want something you have to go in
make the move you have to go and take it
you have to go and ask for it if
somebody has something that you want
then they will not give it to you unless
you go and ask for it and then if they
say yes or no it's it's up to them
that's not under your control but what
is in your control is that you go and
make the approach so uh I hope the guy
is good yeah don't don't go for some
random it should be a guy of good
quality I hope yeah so that's that's my
advice don't don't be shy be bold go and
talk to the guy and see how it goes yeah
all the best
um
says how do you deal with
procrastination
see procrastination is something that's
inbuilt in everybody we want to be
comfortable
we want to be relaxed we want to have
some fun we want to scroll through
whatever it is we want to find some way
to keep us occupied which does not make
us uncomfortable
um
and um
so some people look for motivation they
they listen they watch motivational
videos they hear motivational speeches
and so on see what motivation does is it
it triggers an emotional response in
people but emotions go up and go down
emotions aren't steady emotions are
never steady in anybody even if a person
looks calm all the time the emotions are
there but that person has it under
control so emotions are going to get you
nowhere
how to deal with procrastination
the first thing is you need to have a
goal
you need to have a Target and not a
Target
you need to have a long-term Target and
it should be broken up into smaller
pieces and you need to have your task
for the day okay today I need to do
these two two big things everything else
is okay if I do these two big things
that my day is done and I've I've got a
win for today and then you need to have
the motivation because the target should
mean something to you
so setting idle should be more painful
than going and working for it yeah and
the most important thing is you need to
have a system a process that you follow
every single day
now you know creative people don't like
routine
but even for Creative people routine is
important because that's what produces
the the results
um so you need to have a Target
big Target long-term Target which you
can break down into smaller pieces
you need to have one or two main tasks
for today for each day and then you need
to have a system and a process as which
will help you get those tasks done what
is a system like that I wake up at so
and so time no compromise 7 am I'm up
then I brush then I go out in the sun 10
minutes 15 minutes then I go to the gym
and work out for for 60 minutes or
whatever process it should be something
you follow every single day and then I
do so and so task and then I do so on
the tasks if you have a set process
routine process that you that is
non-negotiable then it is impossible to
procrastinate so you need to create your
system everybody is different for some
people a certain process will work for
for other people a different kind of
process will work you have to find what
works for you
so it's not it's never about emotions
it's never about motivation it's about
creating a process and a system
and you should have a goal if you have
this all of this ready then you will not
ever procrastinate
all the best sir
uh Sheikh Hamza says if Alexander the
Great and chingis Khan were in the same
time period who would win discuss
there's nothing to discuss
with someone to discuss shingles rules
Alex rules
laughs
Anita says Greece was also divided into
city-states and kingdoms yes
and yet it is called one country while
in the case of India the division of
land into republics and kingdoms is used
to point out to say that India was never
one country why
why hypocrisy Western hypocrisy Greece
was always a bunch of city-states who
were always fighting each other read up
the Peloponnesian War
they would have these confederations you
know small alliances from time to time
sometimes they would fight each other
sometimes they would cooperate with each
other you know Sparta against Athens the
these the Athenians
Porsche was involved they they even took
sides with Persia from it's at some
point in time during the Philippines
conflict and uh they were always
fighting each other it was always city
states there was never in unity
and yet today they talk about Greek
culture Greek civilization Greek is one
nation it Greece is one nation but in
the case of India it's like you are
always divided there was no Nation
called India such blatant incredible
hypocrisy I'm so glad that Indians are
now beginning to understand this and
point out these factual inconsistencies
so yeah it's just hypocrisy there's no
other answer
complete total hypocrisy
of the goswami says what if Gandhi had
not come to India
yeah so Gandhi was in South Africa for
20 I don't know 20 plus years yeah
roughly and then then he somehow came to
India and he became overnight the
biggest superstar superhero in Indian
politics and the greatest Freedom
Fighter of them all the question is what
if Gandhi had not come to India well if
Gandhi if Mr Gandhi if Mr Mohandas
Gandhi had not come to India for
whatever reason the British would have
found some other zelinsky in India
thank you
to do the to play that role
the British would have found some other
zelinsky this is a very old game
zelinski
is one of many
yeah there have been lots of zelinski's
and there will be many more in the
future as long as the Anglo-Saxon Empire
persists
so if Mr Gandhi had not come the British
would have found some other zelinski to
play that role in India let's briefly
take some questions from the live chat
because that's what we do
right
uh
okay let's uh
take a question from
a great name like it what do you think
please about the Taliban burning women
from University and crushing women's
rights thanks
um
look personally I believe that there
should be never any discrimination
between between the genders male or
females I believe all human beings
should have the same opportunities in
the same same rights same starting
points that that's from my perspective
because that's the culture and
civilization that I come from we have
always respected women we have always
considered women to be
at least as equal to men if not higher
than men that's the kind of
regard we have always had had for women
and women we have had great women
scholars in India I will not go into the
list
some of the holiest texts of Indians or
civilization the rigveda
much of the texts of the Rigby that have
been written by women female authors so
I we all we Indians believe that women
should be educated and they should get
as much education as they are willing to
get yeah so they should rise to their
food potential full potential the
Taliban or pashtoons they are the
descendants of ancient Indians they're
the descendants of the rig Vedic bhakta
Clan
are stones and today they they they have
a different culture they have imbibed
absorbed a different culture because of
the
because of the process of History
because of what happened in history
and this new culture that that is now
theirs according to that culture they
believe that women should not be
educated the women women have only one
task which is to procreate produce
Offspring and take care of the kitchen
and the home
um
I believe look the principle of
westphalian
uh
the West fire and world order it is
built upon certain principles one of the
principles is non-interference
non-interference means what happens in
my nation is my business what happens in
a different Nation nation state is their
business you don't interfere in my
business I will not interfere in your
business
that's how it goes so I think it's
extraordinarily unfortunate that our
sisters in Afghanistan
are being deprived of education but at
the end of the day uh
maybe that's how it goes in that Nation
but there's a whole set of set of
circumstances is in Iran as well once
again what's happening in Iran is not
India's business it's not India's
problem I I'm I'm sure you would say
it's a very cold-hearted
thing to say
um very
but that's just the way it is that's how
the world works if the people of Iran
want
to change their circumstances they are
welcome to do that yeah we will give
them moral support if the people of
Afghanistan want a different set of
circumstances for themselves it is for
them to change their circumstances
yeah that's how it is so I think it's
unfortunate I think it's not how that's
not how it should be but it's their
business it's their country they are
running the country the Americans have
handed over the country to the Taliban
so if it is anybody's fault it is the
fault of the Americans so that's how it
is yeah
um
okay let's uh let's see some other
questions
is the moon formed by a collision
between the Earth and a rogue Planet uh
it's the the major thesis of the or the
most prominent Theory the theory which
is the most accepted is that there was a
collision between
the Earth and an ancient protoplanet not
a rogue planet
because planets don't have emotions and
agendas they simply Move Along according
to the laws of physics so India so most
likely what happened according to the
mainstream Theory theory is that there
was a collision between the Earth the
ancient Earth and a protoplanet from the
time they took collided and it injected
a huge amount of material which went
into Earth's orbit and eventually
coalesced together into what is now the
moon so that's what is uh believed by a
majority of scientists
uh my thoughts on the God of War Game it
gets a lot of support in India what
would be India's responsive Indian gods
were added in the game I have no idea
about this God of War game I've never
played it I've never seen it
um so yeah I would say that you know if
Indian gods were to be in a game it
should be an Indian game because once
you start
once you allow the these Western
developers to use Indian gods in a game
they're gonna mess up everything they're
gonna disrespect
the way all gods take it take an example
what was the latest Marvel movie with
which had Thor and the female Thor and
all that
I don't remember the name of the movie
Natalie Portman portrays a female
version of Thor with fake muscles and
all that
in that movie there is a scene in which
there's this big assembly of gods all
the various gods of from all parts of
the world except for Indian gods Indian
gods aren't uh shown there but you have
Thor and you have Zeus Zeus is the king
of the god or something like that the
funny thing is that Thor and Zeus are
the same God
and that the same as the Indian God
Indra and in this movie Zeus the Greek
god the Greek version of Indra is shown
as this fat useless guy
very funny guy
not worthy of respect and Thor also is
shown in a kind of disrespectful manner
so they are blatantly disrespecting the
ancient Indo-European Pantheon of gods
Thor and Zeus are the same God the same
Divinity the same is Indra but they have
been portrayed as two different people
in the two antagonists of some kind in
that movie we don't want our Gods to be
pulled into this nonsense so I would say
it's good that they're not they're not
throwing Indian gods on that let's keep
our Gods out of that
um
what are the different philosophies in
Durham West are Western philosophers
built on sanatan Dharma philosophical
ideas listen you want me to talk about
philosophy I can give you it can take
hours
so I would say that that in on my
channel there is this this video
about Indian philosophy I think it's
called Indian philosophy crash course or
something it's just a five minute video
in which I give a very brief and very
rapid overview of the different
philosophical systems in sanatan Dharma
our Western philosophies built on
sanatana Dharma philosophical ideas none
of the Christian philosophies are built
on sanatan Dharma ideas some elements
and aspects have been stolen
especially many of the more modern
philosophers have Wholesales stolen many
of the uh Indian philosophical ideas and
passed them off as their own that's
happened yeah
but if you want an overview of the
various schools of thought in Indian
philosophy go take a look at my channel
search for crash philosophy course crash
course
and you will find a brief video about
that
all right
um what else do we have
do you think this pandemic wave is
really alarming please stop panicking
nothing is gonna go wrong in India the
Chinese have messed up big time the real
what is the root cause of the problems
in China it's the fact that their
vaccines don't work
we all believe that the Chinese of great
scientists and great bio labs and all
that and they are the best in the world
look at the efficiency of the Chinese
vaccine it's abysmal out of all the
vaccines that have been developed for
the coronavirus worldwide the Chinese
vaccine is the worst
and that's the root cause for the
disaster that's unfolding in China right
now
and XI Jin Bing obviously has his pride
so he will not accept any Indian offer
of Indian vaccines and anyway now it's
the situation has gone Way Beyond The
Tipping Point so it's it's a disaster in
China
and and
the variant that is currently you know
spreading through China is one of the O
Micron variants oh Micron right and we
Indians are all vaccinated against this
variant the Indian vaccine is one of the
best if not the best vaccine in the
world
so in India we have used the Indian
covaxine
uh that's the koi Shield also that we
have used it may be a foreign vaccine
but it's also one of one of the better
vaccines so India has made sure that we
do not take the garbage Pfizer vaccine
the uh mRNA vaccine with this with the
doji spike proteins and all that we have
kept it out of India the Americans do
not like it but yeah they can take a
hike
so the Indian vaccine the ones we have
used are the good vaccines they are
efficacious they don't have the ugly
side effects that are killing people
across the West yeah
uh so Indians are now fully vaccinated
and we also have good natural immunity
and all that yeah so there is nothing
for us to worry about
the media will will try to create a
sense of panic ignore it there is
nothing for us in India to worry about
and the other thing is that the
coronavirus is not a very dangerous
virus it affects people who have who are
immunologically compromised people who
have pre-existing conditions like cancer
or diabetes or heart disease or people
who are smokers or people who are
alcoholics or people who are extremely
obese so if you have one of these
preconditions then you may be at a
higher risk of having complications if
you are reasonably healthy there's
nothing for you to worry about so I
would say there is nothing to worry
about please do not get swayed by the
Indian media they will try their best to
create another panic nothing's gonna go
wrong India is perfectly safe India is
perfectly fine
relax take it easy
and keep working keep working that's it
keep going on don't stop and with that
I'm gonna end today's session we have
crossed the two hour mark so that's the
end of today's session thank you so much
for all these wonderful questions once
again I have not been able to take all
the questions but that's how it always
goes so um I will see you all next week
in the next Indian interest live stream
and then the next ask which is live
stream until then take care
and I'll see you soon bye